Guide to the Oregon State Tuberculosis Hospital Collection 1920-1973
Oregon Health Science University Historical Collections Archives
Oregon State Tuberculosis Hospital Collection
1920-1960
1920-1973
2000-001
Oregon Health Science University Historical Collections Archives 3181 SW Sam Jackson Park Road Portland, Oregon, LIB 503-494-3239 peterska@ohsu.edu
2.0 linear feet 2 boxes
Materials are in good condition.
The Oregon State Tuberculosis Hospital was housed in the buildings of the former Oregon Mute School in Salem, OR. The Hospital began admitting patients in 1910. In 1963 due to increase of patients and the combination of the Hospital in Salem with the University of Oregon Medical School State Tuberculosis Hospital. As a result patients on the Portland campus were transferred to the Salem Hospital. The collection contains reports, Birth Certificate Books, Admissions and Discharges, Scrapbooks, Photographs and Correspondence.
Oregon State. Tuberculosis Hospital.
No restrictions on access.
The Tuberculosis Hospital collection consists of photographs and scrapbooks, hospital record books and correspondence pertaining to the operation, staffing and publicity of the Oregon State Tuberculosis Hospital, and its assimilation into the University of Oregon Medical School. The majority of the materials are dated between the early 1920’s and mid 1960’s. Photographs were either loose-leaf, or were taken from one of three scrapbooks detailing the history of the hospital. Record books are dated from 1939 to 1973. See inventory for more details.
The Tuberculosis Hospital Collection was found in a storage closet on the Oregon Health Science University campus. The records were given to Christine Slusarenko, Director of Health Information Services, who transferred them to the OHSU Archives on March 3, 2000. The collection was processed by the OHSU Special Collections staff August 2001.
Biography - Historical Note
In 1894, construction was started in Salem on a building designated to be the Oregon Mute School. The school was abandoned only a short time later because of a lack of adequate roads to its relatively secluded location. Its empty buildings were used to house the newly commissioned Oregon State Tuberculosis Hospital, which began admitting patients in November of 1910.
Doctor H.J. Clement, M.D., was superintendent in 1910 and 1911, and administered the medical program and business. Several new buildings were completed during this period. Later, in 1913 Dr. G.C. Bellinger, M.D., became superintendent. He would remain superintendent until his retirement in 1954.
During the first few years, patients came very slowly, as the idea of a tuberculosis sanatorium was new to the public. Soon, however, the hospital was forced to form a waiting list, and the demand for treatment exceeded the supply of beds. Starting from only fifty beds in 1910, Oregon State Tuberculosis Hospital expanded to 120 beds in 1920, many of which were in open-air pavilions. For the next few decades, the hospital continued to have a significant waiting list, and so kept expanding with new pavilions.
In 1963, the State Legislature combined the Oregon State Tuberculosis Hospital in Salem with the University of Oregon Medical School State Tuberculosis Hospital, which was opened in 1939 on the University’s Portland campus. As a result, patients located in the University State Tuberculosis Hospital on the Portland campus were transferred to the State Hospital in Salem.
Bellinger, Grover C., M.D., Dr.; Clements, Harvey J., M.D.
Oregon
Hospitals, Chronic Disease; Hospitals, Special; Medicine and Health; Tuberculosis
- Box 1
  - Birth Certificate Book – September 1950-September 1952
  - Birth Certificate Book – October 1952-June 1955
  - Admissions and discharges – November 1955-December 1961
  - Admissions and discharges – January 1962-June 1963
  - Admissions and discharges – January 1963-July 1963
  - Admissions and discharges – November 1963-June 1967
  - Admissions and discharges – July 1967-December 1973
  - Outpatient records - 1957-1961
- Box 2
  - Color Slides – ND
  - Surgery Logbook – November 1939-August 1943
  - Surgery Logbook – August 1943-September 1947
  - Surgery Logbook – February 1957-March 1961
  - Surgery Logbook – March 1961-June 1963
- Box 3
  - F1 – Scrapbook 1 Photographs – Early to mid 1930’s
  - F2 – Scrapbook 1 Photographs – Mid to late 1930’s
  - F3 – Scrapbook 2 Photographs – 1910 to early 1920’s
  - F4 – Scrapbook 3 Photographs – Miscellaneous Subfolder containing loose photographs taken from folder within scrapbook 3
  - F5 – Miscellaneous Photographs
  - F6 – Miscellaneous Photographs
  - F7 – Miscellaneous Photographs
- Box 4
  - F8
    - Newspaper Clipping Photocopies – 1956-1966
  - F9
    - “Campus Gram” – Christmas 1966 (x2), February 1967 (x2)
    - Service Awards – 1964, 1965 (2), 1966, 1967 (2 copies)
    - “Oregon Pulse” – 1960, 1963
    - “What’s Going On?” – April 1962, November 1963, October 1964 (2)
    - Annual Report: “The First Half Century” – 1964-65
    - Oregon State Board for Examination and Registration of Graduate Nurses correspondence – 1940-1945
    - Oregon State Medical Society correspondence – May 1932
    - Department of State Correspondence – 1922
    - Utah Tuberculosis Association correspondence – 1934
  - F10
    - 50 Year History – 1961
    - Hospital Standardization Department Survey – 1936
    - Medical Staff of Tuberculosis Hospital 1946-1955
    - Oregon State Tuberculosis Sanatorium by Dr. Bellinger – 1938
    - Correspondence – the Statesman Publishing Co. and Dr. Bellinger – 1927
    - Visiting Tuberculosis Sanatoria of the U.S. B. H. J. Clements – 1910
    - Tuberculosis Commission in session December 29, 1910
    - Traveling Expenses 1915-1916
    - Correspondence to Hon. Board of Control – 1914
    - Annual Report to Hon. Board of Commissioners – Jan 1912
    - Tuberculosis Sanatorium – history and description – March 1913
    - “The Health Pilot” – May 1942
    - Smears and Cultures order slips – 1940-1941
    - Correspondence – Dr. Bellinger with Sadie Drr-Dunbar – January 1925
    - Letter to Dr. Bellinger with aerial photo – June 1933
    - Clipping from Eugene Register Guard on the Hospital with related correspondence – October 1951
    - Dr. Bellinger to A L. Lindbeck regarding publicity items – November 1934
    - Letter to Julia A. O’Brien regarding publicity statement
    - 50th Anniversary Invitations (2 copies) and Memo
    - Leslie Broadcaster, December 1956 (4 copies)
  - F11 - Scrapbook Items/non-photographic materials
    - Rehabilitation Program – May 1947 [scrapbook 1]
    - Letter from H.J. Clements informing of hospital’s opening – September 15, 1910 [scrapbook 2]
    - Oregon State Archives Record of Search – March 1960 [scrapbook 2]
    - Letter to J. G. Lamont re: Children’s Pavilion from Dr. Bellinger – February 1928 [scrapbook 2]
    - Letter to Kenneth C. Ross from R. E. Joseph re: occupational therapy equipment with attached photo [scrapbook 3]
    - Service Award certificates (x3) – 1964, 1965, 1966
    - “Campus Gram” – June 4, 1963, September 20, 1965 [scrapbook 3]
    - Note taken from 1955 [scrapbook 3]
    - 50th Anniversary Invitations 9x2) [scrapbook 3]
    - “Golden” 50th Anniversary program [scrapbook 3]
    - Newspaper articles – 1931-1939, 1952-1967
    - Operative Records – March 3, 1937-May 12, 1963
    - Register of Operations – January 1, 1958-August 20, 1965
  - F12 - Oversized Photographs